<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE lexicon SYSTEM "berry.dtd">
<lexicon>

<entry number="1" heading="Holy, sacred, pure.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="I(ERO/S" strongs="2413" greek="ἱερός" />
<definedWord beta="O(/SIOS" strongs="3741" greek="ὅσιος" />
<definedWord beta="A(/GIOS" strongs="40" greek="ἅγιος" />
<definedWord beta="A(GNO/S" strongs="53" greek="ἁγνός" />
<definedWord beta="SEMNO/S" strongs="4586" greek="σεμνός" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 1. Holy, sacred, pure.</h1>

<h2><g beta="I(ERO/S" strongs="2413" greek="ἱερός" head="false"/>, <g beta="O(/SIOS" strongs="3741" greek="ὅσιος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A(/GIOS" strongs="40" greek="ἅγιος"
head="false"/>, <g beta="A(GNO/S" strongs="53" greek="ἁγνός" head="false"/>, <g beta="SEMNO/S" strongs="4586" greek="σεμνός" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p>None of these words in classical Greek has necessarily any moral
significance. Those which now have such a meaning have developed it in
Biblical Greek. <g beta="I(ERO/S" strongs="2413" greek="ἱερός" head="true"/> means
<em>sacred</em>, implying some special relation to God, so that it may
not be violated. It refers, however, to formal relation rather than to
character. It designates an external relation, which ordinarily is not
an internal relation as well. It is used to describe persons or
things. This is the commonest word for <em>holy</em> in classical
Greek, and expresses their usual conception of holiness, but it is
rare in the N.T. because it fails to express the fullness of the
N.T. conception. <g beta="O(/SIOS" strongs="3741" greek="ὅσιος" head="true"/> used of
persons or things, describes that which is in harmony with the divine
constitution of the moral universe. Hence, it is that which is in
accordance with the general and instinctively felt idea of right,
“what is consecrated and sanctioned by universal law and consent”
(Passow), rather than what is in accordance with any system of
revealed truth. As contrary to <g beta="O(/SIOS" strongs="3741" greek="ὅσιος"
head="false"/>, <em>i.e</em>, as <g beta="A)NO/SIOS" strongs="462" greek="ἀνόσιος"
head="false"/>, the Greeks regarded, <em>e.g.</em>, a marriage between
brother and sister such as was common in Egypt, or the omission of the
rites of sepulture in connection with a relative. <g beta="A(/GIOS" strongs="40" greek="ἅγιος" head="true"/> has probably as its fundamental meaning
<em>separation</em>, <em>i.e.</em>, from the world to God's
service. If not the original meaning, this at any rate is a meaning
early in use. This separation, however, is not chiefly external, it is
rather a separation from evil and defilement. The moral signification
of the word is therefore the prominent one. This word, rare and of
neutral meaning in classical Greek, has been developed in meaning, so
that it expresses the full N.T. conception of holiness as no other
does.  <g beta="A(GNO/S" strongs="53" greek="ἁγνός" head="true"/> is probably
related to <g beta="A(/GIOS" strongs="40" greek="ἅγιος" head="false"/>. It means
specifically <em>pure</em>. But this may be only in a ceremonial
sense, or it may have a moral signification. It sometimes describes
freedom from impurities of the flesh. <g beta="SEMNO/S" strongs="4586" greek="σεμνός"
head="true"/> is that which inspires <em>reverence</em> or
<em>awe</em>. In classical Greek it was often applied to the gods. But
frequently it has the lower idea of that which is humanly venerable,
or even refers simply to externals, as to that which is magnificent,
grand, or impressive.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="2" heading="Sin.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 2. Sin.</h1>

<h2><g beta="A(MARTI/A" strongs="266" greek="ἁμαρτία" head="false"/>, <g beta="A(MA/RTHMA" strongs="265" greek="ἁμάρτημα" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)SE/BEIA" strongs="763" greek="ἀσέβεια" head="false"/>, <g beta="PARAKOH/" strongs="3876" greek="παρακοή"
head="false"/>, <g beta="A)NOMI/A" strongs="458" greek="ἀνομία" head="false"/>, <g beta="PARANOMI/A" strongs="3892" greek="παρανομία" head="false"/>, <g beta="PARA/BASIS" strongs="3847" greek="παράβασις" head="false"/>, <g beta="PARA/PTWMA" strongs="3900" greek="παράπτωμα"
head="false"/>, <g beta="A)GNO/HMA" strongs="51" greek="ἀγνόημα" head="false"/>, <g beta="H(/TTHMA" strongs="2275" greek="ἥττημα" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="A(MARTI/A" strongs="266" greek="ἁμαρτία" head="true"/>. meant originally
<em>the missing of a mark</em>. When applied to moral things the idea
is similar, it is missing the true end of life, and so it is used as a
general term for sin. It means both the act of sinning and the result,
the sin itself. <g beta="A(MA/RTHMA" strongs="265" greek="ἁμάρτημα" head="true"/> means
only the sin itself, not the act, in its particular manifestations as
separate deeds of disobedience to a divine law.  <g beta="A)SE/BEIA" strongs="763" greek="ἀσέβεια" head="true"/> is <em>ungodliness</em>, positive and
active irreligion, a condition of direct opposition to God. <g beta="PARAKOH/" strongs="3876" greek="παρακοή" head="true"/> is strictly <em>failing to
hear</em>, or hearing carelessly and inattentively. The sin is in this
failure to hear when God speaks, and also in the active disobedience
which ordinarily follows. <g beta="A)NOMI/A" strongs="458" greek="ἀνομία"
head="true"/> is <em>lawlessness</em>, contempt of law, a condition or
action not simply without law, as the etymology might indicate, but
contrary to law. The law is usually by implication the Mosaic law. <g beta="PARANOMI/A" strongs="3892" greek="παρανομία" head="true"/>. occurs only once,
<scripRef href="2Pet.2.16">2 Pet. ii. 16</scripRef>, and is
practically equivalent to <g beta="A)NOMI/A" strongs="458" greek="ἀνομία"
head="false"/>. <g beta="PARA/BASIS" strongs="3847" greek="παράβασις" head="true"/> is
<em>transgression</em>, the passing beyond some assigned limit. It is
the breaking of a distinctly recognized commandment. It consequently
means more than <g beta="A(MARTI/A" strongs="266" greek="ἁμαρτία" head="false"/>. <g beta="PARA/PTWMA" strongs="3900" greek="παράπτωμα" head="true"/> is used in different
senses, sometimes in a milder sense, denoting an error, a mistake, a
fault; and sometimes meaning a trespass, a willful sin. <g beta="A)GNO/HMA" strongs="51" greek="ἀγνόημα" head="true"/> occurs only once,
<scripRef href="Heb.9.7">Heb. ix. 7</scripRef>. It indicates
<em>error</em>, sin which to a certain extent is the result of
ignorance. <g beta="H(/TTHMA" strongs="2275" greek="ἥττημα" head="false"/> denotes
<em>being worsted, defeated</em>.  In an ethical sense it means <em>a
failure in duty, a fault</em>. — All these different words may
occasionally but not usually be used simply to describe the same act
from different points of view. The fundamental meanings of these words
may well be summed up in the language of Trench: Sin “may be regarded
as the missing of a mark or aim: it is then <g beta="A(MARTI/A" strongs="266" greek="ἁμαρτία" head="false"/> or <g beta="A(MA/RTHMA" strongs="265" greek="ἁμάρτημα"
head="false"/>; the overpassing or transgression; of a line: it is
then <g beta="PARA/BASIS" strongs="3847" greek="παράβασις" head="false"/>; the
disobedience to a voice: in which case it is <g beta="PARAKOH/" strongs="3876" greek="παρακοή" head="false"/>; the falling where one should have stood
upright: this will be <g beta="PARA/PTWMA" strongs="3900" greek="παράπτωμα"
head="false"/>; ignorance of what one ought to have known: this will
be <g beta="A)GNO/HMA" strongs="51" greek="ἀγνόημα" head="false"/>; diminishing of
that which should have been rendered in full measure, which is <g beta="H(/TTHMA" strongs="2275" greek="ἥττημα" head="false"/>; non-observance of a law,
which is <g beta="A)NOMI/A" strongs="458" greek="ἀνομία" head="false"/> or <g beta="PARANOMI/A" strongs="3892" greek="παρανομία" head="false"/>.”</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="3" heading="Sincere.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 3. Sincere.</h1>

<h2><g beta="A(PLOU=S" strongs="573" greek="ἁπλοῦς" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)KE/RAIOS" strongs="185" greek="ἀκέραιος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)/KAKOS" strongs="172" greek="ἄκακος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)/DOLOS" strongs="97" greek="ἄδολος"
head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="A(PLOU=S" strongs="573" greek="ἁπλοῦς" head="true"/> is literally
<em>spread out without folds</em>, and hence means single, simple,
without complexity of character and motive. In the N.T. this idea of
simplicity is always favorable; in classical Greek the word is also
occasionally used in an unfavorable sense, denoting foolish
simplicity. <g beta="A)KE/RAIOS" strongs="185" greek="ἀκέραιος" head="true"/> also
means <em>simple</em>, literally <em>free from any foreign admixture,
unadulterated, free from disturbing elements</em>. <g beta="A)/KAKOS" strongs="172" greek="ἄκακος" head="true"/> in <scripRef
href="Heb.7.26">Heb. vii. 26</scripRef> means one in whom exists
absence of all evil, and so by implication the presence of all
good. It passes also through the merely negative meaning of absence of
evil, found in S., to the unfavorable meaning of simple, easily
deceived, credulous, which is found in <scripRef href="Rom.16.18">Rom
xvi. 18</scripRef>. <g beta="A)/DOLOS" strongs="97" greek="ἄδολος" head="true"/>
occurring only in <scripRef href="1Pet.2.2">1 Pet. ii. 2</scripRef>,
means <em>sincere</em>, <em>unmixed</em>, <em>without guile</em>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="4" heading="Sins of the tongue.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 4. Sins of the tongue.</h1>

<h2><g beta="MWROLOGI/A" strongs="3473" greek="μωρολογία" head="false"/>, <g beta="AI)SXROLOGI/A" strongs="148" greek="αἰσχρολογία" head="false"/>, <g beta="EU)TRAPELI/A" strongs="2160" greek="εὐτραπελία" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="MWROLOGI/A" strongs="3473" greek="μωρολογία" head="true"/>, used only once in
the N.T., is <em>foolish talking</em>, but this in the Biblical sense
of the word foolish, which implies that it is also sinful.  It is
conversation which is first insipid, then corrupt. It is random talk,
which naturally reveals the vanity and sin of the heart. <g beta="AI)SXROLOGI/A" strongs="148" greek="αἰσχρολογία" head="true"/>, also used once, means
any kind of disgraceful language, especially abuse of others. In
classical Greek it sometimes means distinctively language which leads
to lewdness. <g beta="EU)TRAPELI/A" strongs="2160" greek="εὐτραπελία" head="true"/>,
occurring once, originally meant <em>versatility in
conversation</em>. It acquires, however, an unfavorable meaning, since
polished, refined conversation has a tendency to become evil in many
ways.  The word denotes, then, a subtle form of evil-speaking, sinful
conversation without the coarseness which frequently accompanies it,
but not without its malignity.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="5" heading="Shame, disgrace.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 5. Shame, disgrace.</h1>

<h2><g beta="AI)DW/S" strongs="127" greek="αἰδώς" head="false"/>, <g beta="AI)SXU/NH" strongs="152" greek="αἰσχύνη" head="false"/>, <g beta="E)NTROPH/" strongs="1791" greek="ἐντροπή" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="AI)DW/S" strongs="127" greek="αἰδώς" head="true"/> is the feeling of
<em>innate moral repugnance</em> to doing a dishonorable act. This
moral repugnance is not found in <g beta="AI)SXU/NH" strongs="152" greek="αἰσχύνη"
head="true"/>, which is rather the feeling of <em>disgrace</em> which
results from doing an unworthy thing, or the fear of such disgrace
which serves to prevent its being done. <g beta="AI)DW/S" strongs="127" greek="αἰδώς" head="false"/> is thus the nobler word, <g beta="AI)SXU/NH" strongs="152" greek="αἰσχύνη" head="false"/> having regard chiefly to
the opinions of others. <g beta="AI)DW/S" strongs="127" greek="αἰδώς" head="false"/>
is the fear of doing a shaineful thing, <g beta="AI)SXU/NH" strongs="152" greek="αἰσχύνη" head="false"/> is chiefly the fear of being found
out. “<g beta="AI)DW/S" strongs="127" greek="αἰδώς" head="false"/> would always
restrain a good man from an unworthy act, while <g beta="AI)SXU/NH" strongs="152" greek="αἰσχύνη" head="false"/> might sometimes restrain a bad one”
(Trench). <g beta="E)NTROPH/" strongs="1791" greek="ἐντροπή" head="false"/> stands
somewhat between the other two words in meaning, but in the N.T.
leans to the nobler side, indicating that <em>wholesome shame</em>
which leads a man to consideration of his condition if it is unworthy,
and to a change of conduct for the better. <g beta="SWFROSU/NH" strongs="4997" greek="σωφροσύνη" head="true"/>, <em>self-command</em>, may not seem to
have much in common with these three words. As a matter of fact,
however, it expresses positively that which <g beta="AI)DW/S" strongs="127" greek="αἰδώς" head="false"/> expresses negatively.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="6" heading="Prayer.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 6. Prayer.</h1>

<h2><g beta="EU)XH/" strongs="2171" greek="εὐχή" head="false"/>, <g beta="PROSEUXH/" strongs="4335" greek="προσευχή" head="false"/>, <g beta="DE/HSIS" strongs="1162" greek="δέησις"
head="false"/>, <g beta="E)/NTEUCIS" strongs="1783" greek="ἔντευξις" head="false"/>, <g beta="EU)XARISTI/A" strongs="2169" greek="εὐχαριστία" head="false"/>, <g beta="AI)/THMA" strongs="155" greek="αἴτημα" head="false"/>, <g beta="I(KETHRI/A" strongs="2428" greek="ἱκετηρία"
head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="EU)XH/" strongs="2171" greek="εὐχή" head="true"/>, when it means
<em>prayer</em>, has apparently a general signification.  <g beta="PROSEUXH/" strongs="4335" greek="προσευχή" head="true"/>and <g beta="DE/HSIS" strongs="1162" greek="δέησις" head="true"/> are often used together. <g beta="PROSEUXH/" strongs="4335" greek="προσευχή" head="false"/> is restricted to prayer
to God, while <g beta="DE/HSIS" strongs="1162" greek="δέησις" head="false"/> has no
such restriction. <g beta="DE/HSIS" strongs="1162" greek="δέησις" head="false"/> also
refers chiefly to prayer <em>for particular benefits</em>, while <g beta="PROSEUXH/" strongs="4335" greek="προσευχή" head="false"/> is more general. The
prominent thought in <g beta="E)/NTEUCIS" strongs="1783" greek="ἔντευξις" head="true"/>
is that of boldness and freedom in approach to God. <g beta="EU)XARISTI/A" strongs="2169" greek="εὐχαριστία" head="true"/> is
<em>thanksgiving</em>, the grateful acknowledgment of God’s mercies,
chiefly in prayer. <g beta="AI)/THMA" strongs="155" greek="αἴτημα" head="true"/>,
much like <g beta="DE/HSIS" strongs="1162" greek="δέησις" head="false"/>, denotes a
specific petition for a particular thing. In <g beta="I(KETHRI/A" strongs="2428" greek="ἱκετηρία" head="false"/> the attitude of humility and deprecation
in prayer is specially emphasized. All these words may indicate at
times not different kinds of prayer, but the same prayer viewed from
different stand-points.</p>



</content>
</entry>

<entry number="7" heading="To rebuke; rebuke, accusation">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 7. To rebuke; rebuke, accusation</h1>

<h2><g beta="E)PITIMA/W" strongs="2008" greek="ἐπιτιμάω" head="false"/>,
<g beta="E)LE/GXW" strongs="1651" greek="ἐλέγχω" head="false"/>; <g beta="AI)TI/A" strongs="156" greek="αἰτία" head="false"/>, <g beta="E)/LEGXOS" strongs="1650" greek="ἔλεγχος"
head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="E)PITIMA/W" strongs="2008" greek="ἐπιτιμάω" head="true"/> means simply
<em>to rebuke</em>, in any sense. It may be justly or unjustly, and,
if justly, the rebuke may be heeded or it may not.  <g beta="E)LE/GXW" strongs="1651" greek="ἐλέγχω" head="true"/>, on the other hand, means to rebuke with
sufficient cause, and also effectually, so as to bring the one rebuked
to a confession or at least a conviction of sin. In other words, it
means <em>to convince</em>.  A similar distinction exists between the
nouns <g beta="AI)TI/A" strongs="156" greek="αἰτία" head="false"/> and <g beta="E)/LEGXOS" strongs="1650" greek="ἔλεγχος" head="true"/>. <g beta="AI)TI/A" strongs="156" greek="αἰτία" head="false"/> is an accusation, whether false or
true. <g beta="E)/LEGXOS" strongs="1650" greek="ἔλεγχος" head="false"/> is a charge
which is shown to be true, and often is so confessed by the
accused. It has both a judicial and a moral meaning.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="8" heading="Boaster, proud, insolent.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 8. Boaster, proud, insolent.</h1>

<h2><g beta="A)LAZW/N" strongs="213" greek="ἀλαζών" head="false"/>,
<g beta="U(PERH/FANOS" strongs="5244" greek="ὑπερήφανος" head="false"/>, <g beta="U(BRISTH/S" strongs="5197" greek="ὑβριστής" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="A)LAZW/N" strongs="213" greek="ἀλαζών" head="true"/> is properly <em>a
boaster</em>, who tells great things concerning his own prowess and
achievements, with the implied idea that many of his claims are
false. This word naturally describes a trait which manifests itself in
contact with one’s fellow-men, not one which exists simply within the
heart. <g beta="U(PERH/FANOS" strongs="5244" greek="ὑπερήφανος" head="true"/> describes
one who thinks too highly of himself, describing a trait which is
simply internal, not referring primarily to external manifestation,
although this is implied. It means one who is <em>proud</em>, the
external manifestation when it appears being in the form of
<em>arrogance</em> in dealing with others. <g beta="U(BRISTH/S" strongs="5197" greek="ὑβριστής" head="true"/> describes one who delights in <em>insolent
wrong-doing</em> toward others, finds pleasure in such acts. Cruelty
and lust are two of the many forms which this quality assumes. These
three words occur together in <scripRef
href="Rom.1.30">Ro. i. 30.</scripRef>. They are never used in a good
sense. They may be said to move in a certain sense in an ascending
scale of guilt, designating respectively “the boastful in words, the
proud and overbearing <em>in thoughts</em>, the insolent and injurious
<em>in acts</em>” (Cremer).</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="9" heading="Incorruptible, unfading.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 9. Incorruptible, unfading.</h1>

<h2><g beta="A)/FQARTOS" strongs="862" greek="ἄφθαρτος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)MA/RANTOS" strongs="263" greek="ἀμάραντος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)MARA/NTINOS" strongs="262" greek="ἀμαράντινος" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="A)/FQARTOS" strongs="862" greek="ἄφθαρτος" head="true"/> is properly
<em>incorruptible</em>, unaffected by corruption and decay. It is
applied to God, and to that which is connected with him. <g beta="A)MA/RANTOS" strongs="263" greek="ἀμάραντος" head="true"/> expresses the same idea
in another way.  It means <em>unfading</em>, the root idea being that
it is unaffected by the withering which is common in the case of
flowers. <g beta="A)MARA/NTINOS" strongs="262" greek="ἀμαράντινος" head="true"/>, derived
from <g beta="A)MA/RANTOS" strongs="263" greek="ἀμάραντος" head="false"/>, means
<em>composed of amaranths</em>, <em>i.e.</em>, of unfading
flowers.</p>



</content>
</entry>

<entry number="10" heading="Faultless, unblamed.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 10. Faultless, unblamed.</h1>

<h2><g beta="A)/MWMOS" strongs="299" greek="ἄμωμος" head="false"/>,
<g beta="A)/MEMPTOS" strongs="273" greek="ἄμεμπτος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)NE/GKLHTOS" strongs="410" greek="ἀνέγκλητος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)NEPI/LHPTOS" strongs="423" greek="ἀνεπίληπτος" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="A)/MWMOS" strongs="299" greek="ἄμωμος" head="true"/> is
<em>faultless, without blemish, free from imperfections</em>. It
refers especially to character. <g beta="A)/MEMPTOS" strongs="273"
greek="ἄμεμπτος" head="true"/> is strictly <em>unblamed</em>, one with
whom no fault is found. This of course refers particularly to the
verdict of others upon one. <g beta="A)NE/GKLHTOS" strongs="410"
greek="ἀνέγκλητος" head="true"/> designates one against whom there is
no accusation, implying not acquittal of a charge, but that no charge
has been made. <g beta="A)NEPI/LHPTOS" strongs="423"
greek="ἀνεπίληπτος" head="false"/> means <em>irreprehensible</em>,
designating one who affords nothing upon which an adversary might
seize, in order to make a charge against him.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="11" heading="Regeneration, renovation.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 11. Regeneration, renovation.</h1>

<h2><g beta="PALIGGENESI/A" strongs="3824" greek="παλιγγενεσία"
head="false"/>, <g beta="A)NAKAI/NWSIS" strongs="342" greek="ἀνακαίνωσις" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="PALIGGENESI/A" strongs="3824" greek="παλιγγενεσία" head="true"/> means <em>new
birth</em>. In classical Greek it was used in a weakened sense to
denote a recovery, restoration, revival.  In the N.T. it is used only
twice, but in a higher sense. In <scripRef href="Tit.3.5">Tit.
iii. 5</scripRef> it means <em>new birth</em>, <em>regeneration</em>,
referring to God's act of causing the sinner to pass from the death of
sin into spiritual life in Christ. It has a wider meaning in <scripRef
href="Matt.19.28">Mat. xix. 28</scripRef>, where it is used of the
change which is ultimately to take place in all the universe, its
regeneration, which is the full working out of the change involved in
the regeneration of the individual. <g beta="A)NAKAI/NWSIS" strongs="342" greek="ἀνακαίνωσις" head="false"/>is <em>renewal</em> or
<em>renovation</em>, denoting a continuous process through which man
becomes more fully Christ-like, in which process he is a worker
together with God. Some, as e.g. Cremer, without sufficient reason,
have thought that the early use of <g beta="PALIGGENESI/A" strongs="3824" greek="παλιγγενεσία" head="false"/> as a somewhat technical term, to denote
the Pythagorean doctrine of transmigration, gave to the word a
permanent eschatological coloring, so that in the N .T. it has the
meaning resurrection, especially in <scripRef
href="Matt.19.28">Mat. xix. 28</scripRef>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="12" heading="Murderer.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 12. Murderer.</h1>

<h2><g beta="FONEU/S" strongs="5406" greek="φονεύς" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)NQRWPOKTO/NOS" strongs="443" greek="ἀνθρωποκτόνος" head="false"/>, <g beta="SIKA/RIOS" strongs="4607" greek="σικάριος" head="false"/></h2>

<p>Both in derivation and usage, <g beta="FONEU/S" strongs="5406" greek="φονεύς"
head="true"/> and <g beta="A)NQRWPOKTO/NOS" strongs="443" greek="ἀνθρωποκτόνος"
head="true"/> are distinguished from each other just as the English
<em>murderer</em> from <em>manslayer</em> or <em>homicide</em>. <g beta="SIKA/RIOS" strongs="4607" greek="σικάριος" head="true"/> used only in <scripRef
href="Acts.21.38">Ac. xxi. 38</scripRef>, is the Latin
<em>sicarius</em>, and means <em>an assassin</em>, usually hired for
the work, who furtively stabbed his enemy with a short sword, the
Latin <em>sica</em>. <g beta="FONEU/S" strongs="5406" greek="φονεύς" head="false"/> is
a generic word and may denote a murderer of any kind, <g beta="SIKA/RIOS" strongs="4607" greek="σικάριος" head="false"/> being one of the
specific varieties which it includes.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="13" heading="Anti-Christ, false Christ.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 13. Anti-Christ, false Christ.</h1>

<h2><g beta="YEUDO/XRISTOS" strongs="5580" greek="ψευδόχριστος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)NTI/XRISTOS" strongs="500" greek="ἀντίχριστος" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="YEUDO/XRISTOS" strongs="5580" greek="ψευδόχριστος" head="true"/> means <em>a
false Christ</em>, <em>a pretended Messiah</em>, who sets himself up
instead of Christ, proclaiming that he is Christ.  Some have given
about the same meaning to <g beta="A)NTI/XRISTOS" strongs="500" greek="ἀντίχριστος"
head="true"/>.  But it is much more probable that it means one
diametrically opposed to Christ, one who sets himself up against
Christ, proclaiming that there is no Christ.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="14" heading="Profligacy.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 14. Profligacy.</h1>

<h2><g beta="A)SWTI/A" strongs="810" greek="ἀσωτία" head="false"/>,
<g beta="A)SE/LGEIA" strongs="766" greek="ἀσέλγεια" head="false"/></h2>


<p>The fundamental idea of <g beta="A)SWTI/A" strongs="810" greek="ἀσωτία"
head="false"/> is “wastefulness and riotous excess; of <g beta="A)SE/LGEIA" strongs="766" greek="ἀσέλγεια" head="true"/>, lawless insolence and
wanton caprice” (Trench). <g beta="A)SWTI/A" strongs="810" greek="ἀσωτία"
head="false"/> means reckless and extravagant expenditure, chiefly for
the gratification of one's sensual desires. It denotes a dissolute,
profligate course of life. In <g beta="A)SE/LGEIA" strongs="766" greek="ἀσέλγεια"
ahead="false"/> also there is included the idea of profligacy, often of
lasciviousness, but the fundamental thought is the acknowledging of no
restraints, the insolent doing of whatever one's caprice may
suggest.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="15" heading="Covenant-breaker, implacable.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 15. Covenant-breaker, implacable.</h1>

<h2><g beta="A)SU/NQETOS" strongs="802" greek="ἀσύνθετος"
head="false"/>, <g beta="A)/SPONDOS" strongs="786" greek="ἄσπονδος" head="false"/></h2>


<p>These words are quite similar in their effects, but opposite in
their conception. <g beta="A)SU/NQETOS" strongs="802" greek="ἀσύνθετος" head="true"/>,
occurring only in <scripRef href="Rom.1.31">Ro. i. 31</scripRef>, is
<em>covenant-breaker</em>, one who interrupts a state of peace and
brings on war by disregarding an agreement by which peace is
maintained. <g beta="A)/SPONDOS" strongs="786" greek="ἄσπονδος" head="true"/> is
<em>implacable</em>, one who refuses to agree to any terms or
suggestions of peace. It implies a state of war, and a refusal of
covenant or even of armistice to end it permanently or temporarily. In
the N.T. use both words probably refer not to war in the strict sense
so much as to discord and strife.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="16" heading="Beautiful, graceful.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 16. Beautiful, graceful.</h1>

<h2><g beta="A)STEI=OS" strongs="791" greek="ἀστεῖος" head="false"/>,
<g beta="W(RAI=OS" strongs="5611" greek="ὡραῖος" head="false"/>, <g beta="KALO/S" strongs="2570" greek="καλός" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="A)STEI=OS" strongs="791" greek="ἀστεῖος" head="true"/> is properly one
living in a city, urban. It soon acquires the meaning <em>urbane,
polite, elegant</em>. Then it obtains to a limited extent the meaning
<em>beautiful</em>, although never in the highest degree. <g beta="W(RAI=OS" strongs="5611" greek="ὡραῖος" head="true"/>, from <g beta="W(/RA" strongs="5610" greek="ὥρα" head="false"/>, hour, period, means properly
<em>timely</em>. From that comes the idea of being beautiful, since
nearly everything is beautiful in its hour of fullest perfection.  <g beta="KALO/S" strongs="2570" greek="καλός" head="true"/> is a much higher word. It
means <em>beautiful</em>, physically or morally. It is, however,
distinctly the beauty which comes from harmony, the beauty which
arises from a symmetrical adjustment in right proportion, in other
words, from the harmonious completeness of the object concerned.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="17" heading="Wisdom, knowledge.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 17. Wisdom, knowledge.</h1>

<h2><g beta="SOFI/A" strongs="4678" greek="σοφία" head="false"/>, <g beta="FRO/NHSIS" strongs="5428" greek="φρόνησις" head="false"/>, <g beta="GNW=SIS" strongs="1108" greek="γνῶσις" head="false"/>, <g beta="E)PI/GNWSIS" strongs="1922" greek="ἐπίγνωσις"
head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="SOFI/A" strongs="4678" greek="σοφία" head="true"/> is certainly the
highest word of all these. It is properly <em>wisdom</em>. It denotes
mental excellence in the highest and fullest sense, expressing an
<em>attitude</em> as well as an <em>act</em> of the mind. It
comprehends knowledge and implies goodness, including the striving
after the highest ends, as well as the using of the best means for
their attainment. It is never ascribed to any one but God and good
men, except in a plainly ironical sense. <g beta="FRO/NHSIS" strongs="5428" greek="φρόνησις" head="true"/> is a middle term, sometimes having a
meaning nearly as high as <g beta="SOFI/A" strongs="4678" greek="σοφία"
head="false"/>, sometimes much lower. It means <em>prudence</em>,
<em>intelligence</em>, a skillful adaptation of the means to the end
desired, the end, however, not being necessarily a good one. <g beta="GNW=SIS" strongs="1108" greek="γνῶσις" head="true"/> is <em>knowledge</em>,
<em>cognition</em>, the understanding of facts or truths, or else
<em>insight</em>, <em>discernment</em>. <g beta="E)PI/GNWSIS" strongs="1922" greek="ἐπίγνωσις" head="true"/> has an intensive meaning as compared with
<g beta="GNW=SIS" strongs="1108" greek="γνῶσις" head="false"/>, it is a fuller,
clearer, more thorough knowledge.  The verb <g beta="E)PIGINW/SKW" strongs="1921" greek="ἐπιγινώσκω" head="false"/> has the same intensive force as compared
with <g beta="GINW/SKW" strongs="1097" greek="γινώσκω" head="false"/>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="18" heading="Religious.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 18. Religious.</h1>

<h2><g beta="QEOSEBH/S" strongs="2318" greek="θεοσεβής" head="false"/>,
<g beta="EU)SEBH/S" strongs="2152" greek="εὐσεβής" head="false"/>, <g beta="EU)LABH/S" strongs="2126" greek="εὐλαβής" head="false"/>, <g beta="QRHSKO/S" strongs="2357" greek="θρησκός"
head="false"/>, <g beta="DEISIDAIMONI/A" strongs="1175" greek="δεισιδαιμονία"
head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="QEOSEBH/S" strongs="2318" greek="θεοσεβής" head="false"/>, according to
derivation and usage, means <em>worship of God</em> (or of the gods),
a fulfillment of one's duty towards God.  It is a general term,
meaning <em>religious</em> in a good sense. <g beta="EU)SEBH/S" strongs="2152" greek="εὐσεβής" head="true"/> is distinguished from <g beta="QEOSEBH/S" strongs="2318" greek="θεοσεβής" head="false"/> in two ways. It is used to include the
fulfillment of obligations of all kinds, both towards God and man. It
is thus applied to the fulfillment of the duties involved in human
relations, as towards one's parents. Furthermore, when used in the
higher sense, it means not any kind of worship, but, as the etymology
indicates, the worshipping of God <em>aright</em>. <g beta="EU)LABH/S" strongs="2126" greek="εὐλαβής" head="true"/>, meaning originally <em>careful in
handling</em>, in its religious application means careful in handling
divine things.  It characterizes the anxious and scrupulous
worshipper, careful not to change anything that should be observed in
worship, and fearful of offending: It means <em>devout</em>, and may
be applied to an adherent of any religion, being especially
appropriate to describe the best of the Jewish worshippers. <g beta="QRHSKO/S" strongs="2357" greek="θρησκός" head="true"/> is one who is diligent in
the performance of the <em>outward</em> service of God. It applies
especially to ceremonial worship. <g beta="DEISIDAIMONI/A" strongs="1175" greek="δεισιδαιμονία"
head="true"/>, in accordance with its derivation, makes prominent the
element of <em>fear</em>. It emphasizes strongly the ideas of
dependence and of anxiety for divine favor. It may be used as
practically equivalent to <g beta="QEOSEBH/S" strongs="2318" greek="θεοσεβής"
head="false"/>. Often, however, it implies that the fear which it
makes prominent is an unworthy fear, so that it comes to have the
meaning <em>superstitious</em>. In the
N.T. it is used, as is also the noun <g beta="DEISIDAIMONI/A" strongs="1175" greek="δεισιδαιμονία" head="false"/>, in a purposely neutral sense, meaning
simply <em>religious</em>, neither conveying the highest meaning, nor
plainly implying a lower meaning.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="19" heading="Pure.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 19. Pure.</h1>

<h2><g beta="EI)LIKRINH/S" strongs="1506" greek="εἰλικρινής"
head="false"/><g beta="KAQARO/S" strongs="2513" greek="καθαρός" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)MI/ANTOS" strongs="283" greek="ἀμίαντος" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="EI)LIKRINH/S" strongs="1506" greek="εἰλικρινής" head="true"/> denotes chiefly
that which is pure as being <em>sincere</em>, free from foreign
admixture. <g beta="KAQARO/S" strongs="2513" greek="καθαρός" head="true"/> is that
which is pure as being <em>clean</em>, free from soil or stain. The
meaning of both in the N.T. is distinctly ethical. <g beta="A)MI/ANTOS" strongs="283" greek="ἀμίαντος" head="false"/> is <em>unspotted</em>,
describing that which is far removed from every kind of
contamination.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="20" heading="Assembly, church.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 20. Assembly, church.</h1>

<h2><g beta="SUNAGWGH/" strongs="4864" greek="συναγωγή" head="false"/>,
<g beta="E)KKLHSI/A" strongs="1577" greek="ἐκκλησία" head="false"/>, <g beta="PANH/GURIS" strongs="3831" greek="πανήγυρις" head="false"/></h2>

<p>According to their derivation, <g beta="SUNAGWGH/" strongs="4864" greek="συναγωγή"
head="true"/> is simply <em>an assembly</em>, a mass of people
gathered together; <g beta="E)KKLHSI/A" strongs="1577" greek="ἐκκλησία" head="true"/> is
a narrower word, also <em>an assembly</em>, but including only those
specially <em>called together out of</em> a larger multitude, for the
transaction of business.  <g beta="E)KKLHSI/A" strongs="1577" greek="ἐκκλησία"
head="false"/> usually denotes a somewhat more select company than <g beta="SUNAGWGH/" strongs="4864" greek="συναγωγή" head="false"/>. A significant use of <g beta="E)KKLHSI/A" strongs="1577" greek="ἐκκλησία" head="false"/> in strict harmony with
its derivation was common among the Greeks. It was their common word
for the lawful assembly in a free Greek city of all those possessing
the rights of citizenship, for the transaction of public affairs. They
were <em>summoned out of</em> the whole population, “a select portion
of it, including neither the populace, nor strangers, nor yet those
who had forfeited their civic rights” (Trench). <g beta="SUNAGWGH/" strongs="4864" greek="συναγωγή" head="false"/> had been, before N.T. times, appropriated
to designate <em>a synagogue</em>, a Jewish assembly for worship,
distinct from the Temple, in which sense it is used in the
N.T. Probably for that reason, and also for its greater inherent
etymological fitness, <g beta="E)KKLHSI/A" strongs="1577" greek="ἐκκλησία"
head="false"/> is the word taken to designate <em>a Christian
church</em>, a company of believers who meet for worship. Both these
words, however, are sometimes used in the N.T. in a nontechnical
sense. <g beta="PANH/GURIS" strongs="3831" greek="πανήγυρις" head="true"/>, occurring
only in <scripRef href="Heb.12.23a">Heb. xii. 23</scripRef>, differs
from both, denoting a solemn assembly for festal rejoicing.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="21" heading="Humility, gentleness.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="TAPEINOFROSU/NH" strongs="5012" greek="ταπεινοφροσύνη" />
<definedWord beta="PRA|O/THS" strongs="4236" greek="πρᾳότης" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 21. Humility, gentleness.</h1>

<h2><g beta="TAPEINOFROSU/NH" strongs="5012" greek="ταπεινοφροσύνη"
head="false"/>, <g beta="PRA|O/THS" strongs="4236" greek="πρᾳότης" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="TAPEINOFROSU/NH" strongs="5012" greek="ταπεινοφροσύνη" head="true"/> is
<em>humility</em>, not the making of one's self small when he is
really great, but thinking little of one's self, because this is in a
sense the right estimate for any human being, however great. <g beta="PRA|O/THS" strongs="4236" greek="πρᾳότης" head="true"/> is founded upon this
idea, and goes beyond it. It is the attitude of mind and behavior
which, arising from humility, disposes one to receive with
<em>gentleness</em> and <em>meekness</em> whatever may come to him
from others or from God.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="22" heading="Gentleness.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="PRA|O/THS" strongs="4236" greek="πρᾳότης" />
<definedWord beta="E)PIEI/KEIA" strongs="1932" greek="ἐπιείκεια" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 22. Gentleness.</h1>

<h2><g beta="PRA|O/THS" strongs="4236" greek="πρᾳότης" head="false"/>,
<g beta="E)PIEI/KEIA" strongs="1932" greek="ἐπιείκεια" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p>Both words may be translated <em>gentleness</em>, yet there are
marked differences in meaning. <g beta="PRA|O/THS" strongs="4236" greek="πρᾳότης"
head="false"/> is rather passive, denoting, as has been said above,
see § 21, one's attitude toward others in view of their acts, bad or
good. <g beta="E)PIEI/KEIA" strongs="1932" greek="ἐπιείκεια" head="false"/> is distinctly
active, it is seen in one's deeds toward others, and it usually
implies the relation of superior to inferior. It is fundamentally a
relaxing of strict legal requirements concerning others, yet doing
this in order more fully to carry out the real spirit of the law. It
is <em>clemency</em> in which there is no element of weakness or
injustice.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="23" heading="Desire, lust.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="E)PIQUMI/A" strongs="1939" greek="ἐπιθυμία" />
<definedWord beta="PA/QOS" strongs="3806" greek="πάθος" />
<definedWord beta="O(RMH/" strongs="3730" greek="ὁρμή" />
<definedWord beta="O)/RECIS" strongs="3715" greek="ὄρεξις" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 23. Desire, lust.</h1>

<h2><g beta="E)PIQUMI/A" strongs="1939" greek="ἐπιθυμία" head="false"/>, <g beta="PA/QOS" strongs="3806" greek="πάθος" head="false"/>, <g beta="O(RMH/" strongs="3730" greek="ὁρμή" head="false"/>, <g beta="O)/RECIS" strongs="3715" greek="ὄρεξις" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="E)PIQUMI/A" strongs="1939" greek="ἐπιθυμία" head="true"/> is the broadest of
these words. Its meaning may be good, but it is usually bad. It
denotes any natural desire or appetite, usually with the implication
that it is a depraved desire. <g beta="PA/QOS" strongs="3806" greek="πάθος"
head="true"/> has not as broad a meaning as in classical Greek, but
denotes evil desire, chiefly, however, as a condition of the soul
rather than in active operation. <g beta="O(RMH/" strongs="3730" greek="ὁρμή"
head="false"/> indicates <em>hostile</em> motion toward an object,
either for seizing or repelling. <g beta="O)/RECIS" strongs="3715" greek="ὄρεξις"
head="false"/> is a desire or appetite, especially seeking the object
of gratification in order to make it one’s own.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="24" heading="Affliction.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="QLI=YIS" strongs="2347" greek="θλῖψις" />
<definedWord beta="STENOXWRI/A" strongs="4730" greek="στενοχωρία" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 24. Affliction.</h1>

<h2><g beta="QLI=YIS" strongs="2347" greek="θλῖψις" head="false"/>, <g beta="STENOXWRI/A" strongs="4730" greek="στενοχωρία" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="QLI=YIS" strongs="2347" greek="θλῖψις" head="true"/> according to its
derivation means <em>pressure</em>. In its figurative sense it is that
which presses upon the spirit, <em>affliction</em>. <g beta="STENOXWRI/A" strongs="4730" greek="στενοχωρία" head="true"/> meant originally <em>a
narrow, confined space</em>. It denotes affliction as arising from
cramping circumstances. In use it cannot always be distinguished from
<g beta="QLI=YIS" strongs="2347" greek="θλῖψις" head="false"/>, but it is ordinarily a
stronger word.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="25" heading="Bad, evil.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="KAKO/S" strongs="2556" greek="κακός" />
<definedWord beta="PONHRO/S" strongs="4190" greek="πονηρός" />
<definedWord beta="FAU=LOS" strongs="5337" greek="φαῦλος" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 25. Bad, evil.</h1>

<h2><g beta="KAKO/S" strongs="2556" greek="κακός" head="false"/>, <g beta="PONHRO/S" strongs="4190" greek="πονηρός" head="false"/>, <g beta="FAU=LOS" strongs="5337" greek="φαῦλος" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p>These words may be used with very little distinction of meaning,
but often the difference is marked. <g beta="KAKO/S" strongs="2556" greek="κακός"
head="true"/> frequently means <em>evil</em> rather negatively,
referring to the absence of the qualities which constitute a person or
thing what it should be or what it claims to be. It is also used
meaning <em>evil</em> in a moral sense.  It is a general antithesis to
<g beta="A)GAQO/S" strongs="18" greek="ἀγαθός" head="false"/>. <g beta="PONHRO/S" strongs="4190" greek="πονηρός" head="false"/> is a word at once stronger and more
active, it means <em>mischief-making</em>, delighting in injury, doing
evil to others, dangerous, destructive. <g beta="KAKO/S" strongs="2556" greek="κακός"
head="false"/> describes the quality according to its nature, <g beta="PONHRO/S" strongs="4190" greek="πονηρός" head="false"/>, according to its
effects. <g beta="FAU=LOS" strongs="5337" greek="φαῦλος" head="false"/> is the bad
chiefly as the <em>worthless</em>, the good for nothing.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="26" heading="Punishment">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 26. Punishment</h1>

<h2><g beta="TIMWRI/A" strongs="5098" greek="τιμωρία" head="false"/>, <g beta="KO/LASIS" strongs="2851" greek="κόλασις" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="TIMWRI/A" strongs="5098" greek="τιμωρία" head="true"/> in classical and
N.T. usage denotes especially the vindicative character of punishment,
it is the punishment in relation to the <em>punisher</em>. <g beta="KO/LASIS" strongs="2851" greek="κόλασις" head="false"/> in classical Greek meant
usually punishment which aimed at the reformation of the offender. But
sometimes in later Greek, and always in the N.T., the idea of
reformation seems to disappear, so that there remains simply the idea
of punishment, but viewed in relation to the <em>punished</em>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="27" heading="To pollute.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 27. To pollute.</h1>

<h2><g beta="MIAI/NW" strongs="3392" greek="μιαίνω" head="false"/>, <g beta="MOLU/NW" strongs="3435" greek="μολύνω" head="false"/></h2>


<p><g beta="MIAI/NW" strongs="3392" greek="μιαίνω" head="true"/> meant originally
<em>to stain</em>, as with color. <g beta="MOLU/NW" strongs="3435" greek="μολύνω"
head="true"/> meant originally <em>to smear over</em>, as with mud or
filth, always having a bad meaning, while the meaning of <g beta="MIAI/NW" strongs="3392" greek="μιαίνω" head="false"/> might be either good or
bad. According to classical Greek, <g beta="MIAI/NW" strongs="3392" greek="μιαίνω"
head="false"/> has a religious meaning, <em>to profane</em>, while <g beta="MOLU/NW" strongs="3435" greek="μολύνω" head="false"/> is simply <em>to
spoil</em>, <em>disgrace</em>.  As ethically applied in the N.T. they
have both practically the same meaning, <em>to pollute</em>,
<em>defile</em>. It is, however, true that <g beta="MIAI/NW" strongs="3392" greek="μιαίνω" head="false"/>, to judge from classical usage, refers
chiefly to the effect of the act not on the individual, but on others,
on the community.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="28" heading="To do.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="POIE/W" strongs="4160" greek="ποιέω" />
<definedWord beta="PRA/SSW" strongs="4238" greek="πράσσω" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 28. To do.</h1>

<h2><g beta="POIE/W" strongs="4160" greek="ποιέω" head="false"/>, <g beta="PRA/SSW" strongs="4238" greek="πράσσω" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p>These words are often used interchangeably, but in many cases a
distinction can be drawn. <g beta="POIE/W" strongs="4160" greek="ποιέω" head="true"/>
refers more to the object and end of an act, <g beta="PRA/SSW" strongs="4238" greek="πράσσω" head="true"/> rather to the means by which the object is
attained. Hence, while <g beta="POIE/W" strongs="4160" greek="ποιέω" head="false"/>
means <em>to accomplish</em>, <g beta="PRA/SSW" strongs="4238" greek="πράσσω"
head="false"/> may mean nothing more than merely <em>to busy one’s
self about</em>. <g beta="POIE/W" strongs="4160" greek="ποιέω" head="false"/> often
means to do a thing once for all, <g beta="PRA/SSW" strongs="4238" greek="πράσσω"
head="false"/>, to do continually or repeatedly. From these
distinctions it follows that <g beta="POIE/W" strongs="4160" greek="ποιέω"
head="false"/>, being on the whole the higher word, is more often used
of doing good, <g beta="PRA/SSW" strongs="4238" greek="πράσσω" head="false"/> more
frequently of doing evil.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="29" heading="Fleshly, fleshy, sensual.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="SARKIKO/S" strongs="4559" greek="σαρκικός" />
<definedWord beta="SA/RKINOS" strongs="4560" greek="σάρκινος" />
<definedWord beta="YUXIKO/S" strongs="5591" greek="ψυχικός" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 29. Fleshly, fleshy, sensual.</h1>

<h2><g beta="SARKIKO/S" strongs="4559" greek="σαρκικός" head="false"/>,
<g beta="SA/RKINOS" strongs="4560" greek="σάρκινος" head="false"/>, <g beta="YUXIKO/S" strongs="5591" greek="ψυχικός" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="SARKIKO/S" strongs="4559" greek="σαρκικός" head="true"/> means
<em>fleshly</em>, that which is controlled by the wrong desires which
rule in the flesh, flesh often being understood in its broad sense,
see <g beta="SA/RC" strongs="4561" greek="σάρξ" head="false" ref="external"/>. It
describes a man who gives the flesh the dominion in his life, a place
which does not belong to it by right. It means distinctly opposed to
the Spirit of God, anti-spiritual. <g beta="SA/RKINOS" strongs="4560" greek="σάρκινος"
head="true"/> properly means <em>fleshy</em>, made of flesh, flesh
being the material of which it is composed. When given a bad meaning,
however, it is plainly similar to <g beta="SARKIKO/S" strongs="4559" greek="σαρκικός"
head="false"/>, but according to Trench not so strong, denoting one as
unspiritual, undeveloped, rather than anti-spiritual. Others, as
Cremer and Thayer, with more probability make <g beta="SA/RKINOS" strongs="4560" greek="σάρκινος" head="false"/> the stronger, it describes one who is
flesh, wholly given up to the flesh, rooted in the flesh, rather than
one who simply acts according to the flesh (<g beta="SARKIKO/S" strongs="4559" greek="σαρκικός" head="false"/>). There is much confusion between the two
in the N.T. manuscripts. <g beta="YUXIKO/S" strongs="5591" greek="ψυχικός"
head="true"/> has a meaning somewhat similar to <g beta="SARKIKO/S" strongs="4559" greek="σαρκικός" head="false"/>. Both are used in contrast with <g beta="PNEUMATIKO/S" strongs="4152" greek="πνευματικός" head="false"/>. But <g beta="SARKIKO/S" strongs="4559" greek="σαρκικός" head="false"/> has really a distinct
meaning, describing the life which is controlled by the <g beta="YUXH/" strongs="5590" greek="ψυχή" head="false" ref="external"/>. It denotes,
therefore, that which belongs to the animal life, or that which is
controlled simply by the appetites and passions of the sensuous
nature.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="30" heading="Mercy, compassion.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 30. Mercy, compassion.</h1>

<h2><g beta="E)/LEOS" strongs="1656" greek="ἔλεος" head="false"/>, <g beta="OI)KTIRMO/S" strongs="3628" greek="οἰκτιρμός" head="false"/></h2>

<p>Both words denote sympathy, fellow-feeling with misery, mercy,
compassion. <g beta="E)/LEOS" strongs="1656" greek="ἔλεος" head="true"/>, however,
manifests itself chiefly in acts rather than words, while <g beta="OI)KTIRMO/S" strongs="3628" greek="οἰκτιρμός" head="true"/> is used rather of the
inward feeling of compassion which abides in the heart. A criminal
might ask for <g beta="E)/LEOS" strongs="1656" greek="ἔλεος" head="false"/>,
<em>mercy</em>, from his judge; but hopeless suffering may be the
object of <g beta="OI)KTIRMO/S" strongs="3628" greek="οἰκτιρμός" head="false"/>,
<em>compassion</em>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="31" heading="To love.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 31. To love.</h1>

<h2><g beta="A)GAPA/W" strongs="25" greek="ἀγαπάω" head="false"/>,
<g beta="FILE/W" strongs="5368" greek="φιλέω" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="A)GAPA/W" strongs="25" greek="ἀγαπάω" head="true"/>, and not <g beta="FILE/W" strongs="5368" greek="φιλέω" head="true"/>, is the word used of God's
love to men, <g beta="FILANQRWPI/A" strongs="5363" greek="φιλανθρωπία" head="false"/> is,
however, once used with this meaning, <scripRef
href="Tit.3.4">Tit. iii. 4</scripRef>.  <g beta="A)GAPA/W" strongs="25" greek="ἀγαπάω" head="false"/> is also the word ordinarily used of men’s
love to God, but <g beta="FILE/W" strongs="5368" greek="φιλέω" head="false"/> is once
so used, <scripRef href="1Cor.16.22">I Cor. xvi. 22</scripRef>. <g beta="A)GAPA/W" strongs="25" greek="ἀγαπάω" head="false"/> is the word used of love
to one’s enemies. The interchange of the words in <scripRef
href="John.21.15-John.21.17">Jn. xxi. 15-17</scripRef> is very
interesting and instructive.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="32" heading="To will, to wish.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="BOU/LOMAI" strongs="1014" greek="βούλομαι" />
<definedWord beta="QE/LW" strongs="2309" greek="θέλω" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 32. To will, to wish.</h1>

<h2><g beta="BOU/LOMAI" strongs="1014" greek="βούλομαι" head="false"/>, <g beta="QE/LW" strongs="2309" greek="θέλω" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p>In many cases these two words are used without appreciable
distinction, meaning <em>conscious willing, purpose</em>. But
frequently it is evident that a difference is intended, although there
is much difference of opinion as to the exact distinction. Thayer says
that <g beta="BOU/LOMAI" strongs="1014" greek="βούλομαι" head="true"/> “seems to
designate the will which follows deliberation,” <g beta="QE/LW" strongs="2309" greek="θέλω" head="true"/>, “the will which proceeds from
inclination.”  Grimm, on the other hand, says that <g beta="QE/LW" strongs="2309" greek="θέλω" head="false"/> gives prominence to the emotive element,
<g beta="BOU/LOMAI" strongs="1014" greek="βούλομαι" head="false"/> to the rational and
volitive; <g beta="QE/LW" strongs="2309" greek="θέλω" head="false"/> signifies the
choice, while <g beta="BOU/LOMAI" strongs="1014" greek="βούλομαι" head="false"/> marks
the choice as deliberate and intelligent. The view of Cremer on the
whole seems preferable to any other. According to this view, <g beta="BOU/LOMAI" strongs="1014" greek="βούλομαι" head="false"/> has the wider range of
meaning, but <g beta="QE/LW" strongs="2309" greek="θέλω" head="false"/> is the
stronger word, <g beta="QE/LW" strongs="2309" greek="θέλω" head="false"/> denotes
the active resolution, the will urging on to action, see <scripRef
href="Rom.7.15">Ro. vii. 15</scripRef>, while <g beta="BOU/LOMAI" strongs="1014" greek="βούλομαι" head="false"/> is rather to have in thought, to intend,
to be determined. <g beta="BOU/LOMAI" strongs="1014" greek="βούλομαι" head="false"/>
sometimes means no more than to have an inclination, see <scripRef
href="Acts.23.15">Ac. xxiii. 15</scripRef>. Instructive examples of
the use of the two words in close proximity are found in <scripRef
href="Mark.15.9;Mark.15.15">Mar. xv. 9, 15</scripRef>, and especially
<scripRef href="Matt.1.19">Mat. i. 19</scripRef>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="33" heading="Schism.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 33. Schism.</h1>

<h2><g beta="SXI/SMA" strongs="4978" greek="σχίσμα" head="false"/>, <g beta="AI(/RESIS" strongs="139" greek="αἵρεσις" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="SXI/SMA" strongs="4978" greek="σχίσμα" head="true"/> is <em>actual
division, separation</em>. <g beta="AI(/RESIS" strongs="139" greek="αἵρεσις"
head="true"/> is rather <em>the separating tendency</em>, so it is
really more fundamental than <g beta="SXI/SMA" strongs="4978" greek="σχίσμα"
head="false"/>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="34" heading="Mind, understanding.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 34. Mind, understanding.</h1>

<h2><g beta="NOU=S" strongs="3563" greek="νοῦς" head="false"/>, <g beta="DIA/NOIA" strongs="1271" greek="διάνοια" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="NOU=S" strongs="3563" greek="νοῦς" head="true"/> is distinctly <em>the
reflective consciousness</em>, “the organ of moral thinking and
knowing, the intellectual organ of moral sentiment” (Cremer). <g beta="DIA/NOIA" strongs="1271" greek="διάνοια" head="true"/> meant originally
<em>activity of thinking</em>, but has borrowed from <g beta="NOU=S" strongs="3563" greek="νοῦς" head="false"/> its common meaning of <em>faculty of
thought</em>. It is more common than <g beta="NOU=S" strongs="3563" greek="νοῦς"
head="false"/>, and has largely replaced it in its usual meanings.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="35" heading="Law.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 35. Law.</h1>

<h2><g beta="NO/MOS" strongs="3551" greek="νόμος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)/QESMOS" strongs="113" greek="ἄθεσμος" head="false"/>, <g beta="E)NTOLH/" strongs="1785" greek="ἐντολή" head="false"/>, <g beta="DO/GMA" strongs="1378" greek="δόγμα"
head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="NO/MOS" strongs="3551" greek="νόμος" head="true"/> is the common word
meaning <em>law</em>. It may mean law in general. In the N.T.,
however, it usually means the law of God, and most frequently the
Mosaic law. <g beta="A)/QESMOS" strongs="113" greek="ἄθεσμος" head="true"/> is law
considered with special reference to the authority on which it
rests. <g beta="E)NTOLH/" strongs="1785" greek="ἐντολή" head="true"/> is more
specific, being used of a particular command. <g beta="DO/GMA" strongs="1378" greek="δόγμα" head="true"/> is an authoritative conclusion, a
proposition which it is expected that all will recognize as
universally binding.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="36" heading="Type, image.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 36. Type, image.</h1>

<h2><g beta="TU/POS" strongs="5179" greek="τύπος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)NTI/TUPON" strongs="499" greek="ἀντίτυπον" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="TU/POS" strongs="5179" greek="τύπος" head="true"/> has many meanings,
among the most common being <em>image, pattern</em> or <em>model</em>,
and <em>type</em>. In the last sense it means a person or thing
prefiguring a future person or thing, <em>e.g.</em>, Adam as a type of
Christ, <scripRef href="Rom.5.14">Ro. v. 14</scripRef>. <g beta="A)NTI/TUPON" strongs="499" greek="ἀντίτυπον" head="true"/>, as used in <scripRef
href="1Pet.3.21">1 Pet. iii. 21</scripRef>, is by Thayer and many
others thought to correspond to <g beta="TU/POS" strongs="5179" greek="τύπος"
head="false"/> as its counterpart, in the sense which the English word
antitype suggests. By Cremer it is rather given the meaning
<em>image</em>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="37" heading="To ask.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 37. To ask.</h1>

<h2><g beta="AI)TE/W" strongs="154" greek="αἰτέω" head="false"/>, <g beta="E)RWTA/W" strongs="2065" greek="ἐρωτάω" head="false"/></h2>

<p>Thayer, as opposed to Trench and others, would make the distinction
between these two words to be this: “<g beta="AI)TE/W" strongs="154" greek="αἰτέω"
head="true"/> signifies to ask for something to be given, not done,
giving prominence to the thing asked for rather than the person, and
hence is rarely used in exhortation. <g beta="E)RWTA/W" strongs="2065" greek="ἐρωτάω"
head="false"/>, on the other hand, is to request a person to do
(rarely to give) something; referring more directly to the person, it
is naturally used in exhortation, etc.”</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="38" heading="World, age.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 38. World, age.</h1>

<h2><g beta="AI)W/N" strongs="165" greek="αἰών" head="false"/>, <g beta="KO/SMOS" strongs="2889" greek="κόσμος" head="false"/></h2>

<p>It is only in a part of their meanings that these two words are in
any real sense synonymous, and it is that part which is here
considered. Both A. V. and R. V. often translate <g beta="AI)W/N" strongs="165" greek="αἰών" head="true"/> by <em>world</em>, thus obscuring the
distinction between it and <g beta="KO/SMOS" strongs="2889" greek="κόσμος"
head="true"/>.  <g beta="AI)W/N" strongs="165" greek="αἰών" head="false"/> is
usually better expressed by <em>age</em>, it is the world at a given
time, a particular period in the world's history. <g beta="KO/SMOS" strongs="2889" greek="κόσμος" head="false"/> has very frequently an unfavorable
meaning, denoting the inhabitants of the world, mankind in general, as
opposed to God. A similar meaning is often attached to <g beta="AI)W/N" strongs="165" greek="αἰών" head="false"/>, it means the spirit of the
age, often in an unfavorable sense. See <scripRef
href="Eph.2.2">Ep. ii. 2</scripRef>, where both words occur
together. An exceptional meaning for the plural of <g beta="AI)W/N" strongs="165" greek="αἰών" head="false"/> is found in <scripRef
href="Heb.1.2">Heb. i. 2</scripRef> and <scripRef
href="Heb.6.3">xi. 3</scripRef>, where it denotes the worlds,
apparently in reference to space rather than time.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="39" heading="Rest.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 39. Rest.</h1>

<h2><g beta="A)NA/PAUSIS" strongs="372" greek="ἀνάπαυσις"
head="false"/>, <g beta="A)/NESIS" strongs="425" greek="ἄνεσις" head="false"/></h2>

<p>Both words in a certain sense mean <em>rest</em>, but from
different stand-points. <g beta="A)NA/PAUSIS" strongs="372" greek="ἀνάπαυσις"
head="true"/> is rest which comes by cessation from labor, which may
be simply temporary. <g beta="A)/NESIS" strongs="425" greek="ἄνεσις" head="true"/>
means literally the relaxation of strings which have been drawn
tight. Hence, it is used to designate ease, especially that which
comes by relaxation of unfavorable conditions of any kind, such as
affliction.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="40" heading="Wind.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 40. Wind.</h1>

<h2><g beta="PNEU=MA" strongs="4151" greek="πνεῦμα" head="false"/>, <g beta="PNOH/" strongs="4157" greek="πνοή" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)/NEMOS" strongs="417" greek="ἄνεμος" head="false"/>, <g beta="LAI=LAY" strongs="2978" greek="λαῖλαψ"
head="false"/>, <g beta="QU/ELLA" strongs="2366" greek="θύελλα" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="PNEU=MA" strongs="4151" greek="πνεῦμα" head="true"/> when used in its
lower meaning to denote wind means simply <em>an ordinary wind</em>, a
regularly blowing current of air of considerable force. <g beta="PNOH/" strongs="4157" greek="πνοή" head="true"/> is distinguished from it as
being a gentler motion of the air. <g beta="A)/NEMOS" strongs="417" greek="ἄνεμος"
head="true"/>, on the other hand, is more forcible than <g beta="PNEU=MA" strongs="4151" greek="πνεῦμα" head="false"/>, it is the strong, often
the tempestuous, wind. <g beta="LAI=LAY" strongs="2978" greek="λαῖλαψ" head="true"/>
is the violent fitful wind which accompanies a heavy shower. <g beta="QU/ELLA" strongs="2366" greek="θύελλα" head="false"/> is more violent than any
of the others, and often implies a conflict of opposing winds.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="41" heading="Old.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 41. Old.</h1>

<h2><g beta="PALAIO/S" strongs="3820" greek="παλαιός" head="false"/>,
<g beta="A)RXAI=OS" strongs="744" greek="ἀρχαῖος" head="false"/></h2>

<p>According to their derivation, <g beta="PALAIO/S" strongs="3820" greek="παλαιός"
head="true"/> is that which has been in existence for a long time, <g beta="A)RXAI=OS" strongs="744" greek="ἀρχαῖος" head="true"/> that which has been from
the beginning. In use, at times no distinction can be drawn.  Often,
however, <g beta="A)RXAI=OS" strongs="744" greek="ἀρχαῖος" head="false"/> does denote
distinctively that which has been from the beginning, and so it
reaches back to a point of time beyond <g beta="PALAIO/S" strongs="3820" greek="παλαιός" head="false"/>. <g beta="PALAIO/S" strongs="3820" greek="παλαιός"
head="false"/> has often the secondary meaning of that which is old
and so worn out, having suffered more or less from the injuries and
ravages of time, its opposite in this sense being <g beta="KAINO/S" strongs="2537" greek="καινός" head="false" ref="true" entry="52"/>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="42" heading="Harsh, austere.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 42. Harsh, austere.</h1>

<h2><g beta="AU)STHRO/S" strongs="840" greek="αὐστηρός" head="false"/>,
<g beta="SKLHRO/S" strongs="4642" greek="σκληρός" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="AU)STHRO/S" strongs="840" greek="αὐστηρός" head="true"/> has not
necessarily an unfavorable meaning. It is well represented by the word
<em>austere</em>, it means one who is earnest and severe, strict in
his ways, opposed to all levity. By implication it may have the
unfavorable meaning of harshness or moroseness. <g beta="SKLHRO/S" strongs="4642" greek="σκληρός" head="true"/> has always an unfavorable meaning.  It
indicates one who is uncivil, intractable, rough and harsh.  There is
in it the implication of inhumanity.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="43" heading="Darkness.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 43. Darkness.</h1>

<h2><g beta="SKO/TOS" strongs="4655" greek="σκότος" head="false"/>, <g beta="GNO/FOS" strongs="1105" greek="γνόφος" head="false"/>, <g beta="ZO/FOS" strongs="2217" greek="ζόφος" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)XLU/S" strongs="887" greek="ἀχλύς"
head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="SKO/TOS" strongs="4655" greek="σκότος" head="true"/> is a general word,
meaning <em>darkness</em> in any sense.  <g beta="GNO/FOS" strongs="1105" greek="γνόφος" head="true"/> usually refers to darkness that
accompanies a storm.  <g beta="ZO/FOS" strongs="2217" greek="ζόφος" head="false"/>
meant originally <em>the gloom</em> of twilight. It was then applied
in classical Greek to the darkness of the underworld, the gloom of a
sunless region. The latter meaning seems to be practically the one
which the word has in the N.T. <g beta="A)XLU/S" strongs="887" greek="ἀχλύς"
head="true"/> is specifically a misty darkness.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="44" heading="People, nation.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 44. People, nation.</h1>

<h2><g beta="LAO/S" strongs="2992" greek="λαός" head="false"/>, <g beta="E)/QNOS" strongs="1484" greek="ἔθνος" head="false"/>, <g beta="DH=MOS" strongs="1218" greek="δῆμος" head="false"/>, <g beta="O)/XLOS" strongs="3793" greek="ὄχλος"
head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="LAO/S" strongs="2992" greek="λαός" head="true"/> is a word which is
usually limited in use to the chosen people, Israel. <g beta="E)/QNOS" strongs="1484" greek="ἔθνος" head="true"/> in the singular is a general term for
nation, applied to any nation, even to the Jews. In the plural it
ordinarily denotes all mankind aside from the Jews and in contrast
with them, the Gentiles. <g beta="DH=MOS" strongs="1218" greek="δῆμος" head="true"/>
is a people, especially organized and convened together, and
exercising their rights as citizens. <g beta="O)/XLOS" strongs="3793" greek="ὄχλος"
head="true"/> is <em>a crowd</em>, an unorganized multitude, especially
composed of those who have not the rights and privileges of free
citizens.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="45" heading="Servant, slave.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 45. Servant, slave.</h1>

<h2><g beta="DOU=LOS" strongs="1401" greek="δοῦλος" head="false"/>, <g beta="QERA/PWN" strongs="2324" greek="θεράπων" head="false"/>, <g beta="DIA/KONOS" strongs="1249" greek="διάκονος" head="false"/>, <g beta="OI)KE/THS" strongs="3610" greek="οἰκέτης"
head="false"/>, <g beta="U(PHRE/THS" strongs="5257" greek="ὑπηρέτης" head="false"/></h2>


<p><g beta="DOU=LOS" strongs="1401" greek="δοῦλος" head="true"/> is the usual word for
<em>slave</em>, one who is permanently in servitude, in subjection to
a master. <g beta="QERA/PWN" strongs="2324" greek="θεράπων" head="true"/> is simply one
who renders service at a particular time, sometimes as a slave, more
often as a freeman, who renders voluntary service prompted by duty or
love. It denotes one who serves, <em>in his relation to a
person</em>. <g beta="DIA/KONOS" strongs="1249" greek="διάκονος" head="true"/> also may
designate either a slave or a freeman, it denotes a servant viewed
<em>in relation to his work</em>. <g beta="OI)KE/THS" strongs="3610" greek="οἰκέτης"
head="true"/> designates a slave, sometimes being practically
equivalent to <g beta="DOU=LOS" strongs="1401" greek="δοῦλος" head="false"/>. Usually,
however, as the etymology of the term indicates, it means a slave as a
member of the household, not emphasizing the servile idea, but rather
the relation which would tend to mitigate the severity of his
condition. <g beta="U(PHRE/THS" strongs="5257" greek="ὑπηρέτης" head="false"/> means
literally <em>an under-rower</em>, and was used to describe an
ordinary rower on a war-galley. It is then used, as in the N.T., to
indicate any man, not a slave, who served in a subordinate position
under a superior.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="46" heading="To adulterate.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="KAPHLEU/W" strongs="2585" greek="καπηλεύω" />
<definedWord beta="DOLO/W" strongs="1389" greek="δολόω" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 46. To adulterate.</h1>

<h2><g beta="KAPHLEU/W" strongs="2585" greek="καπηλεύω" head="false"/>,
<g beta="DOLO/W" strongs="1389" greek="δολόω" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p>Both these words mean <em>to adulterate</em>, and some maintain
that they are practically identical. But it is more probable that <g beta="DOLO/W" strongs="1389" greek="δολόω" head="true"/> means simply to adulterate,
while <g beta="KAPHLEU/W" strongs="2585" greek="καπηλεύω" head="true"/> conveys the idea
of adulterating for the sake of making an unjust profit by the
process.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="47" heading="Animal.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="ZW=ON" strongs="2226" greek="ζῶον" />
<definedWord beta="QHRI/ON" strongs="2342" greek="θηρίον" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 47. Animal.</h1>

<h2><g beta="ZW=ON" strongs="2226" greek="ζῶον" head="false"/>, <g beta="QHRI/ON" strongs="2342" greek="θηρίον" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="ZW=ON" strongs="2226" greek="ζῶον" head="true"/> is a general term,
meaning <em>living creature</em>, which may include all living beings,
in classical Greek even including man.  In the N.T. it means
ordinarily <em>animal</em>. <g beta="QHRI/ON" strongs="2342" greek="θηρίον"
head="true"/> is <em>beast</em>, usually wild beast. It implies
perhaps not necessarily wildness and ferocity, but at least a certain
amount of brutality which is wanting in <g beta="ZW=ON" strongs="2226" greek="ζῶον"
head="false"/>. <g beta="ZW=ON" strongs="2226" greek="ζῶον" head="false"/>
emphasizes the qualities in which animals are akin to man, <g beta="QHRI/ON" strongs="2342" greek="θηρίον" head="false"/>, those in which they are
inferior.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="48" heading="Sea.">
<definedWords>
</definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 48. Sea.</h1>

<h2><g beta="QA/LASSA" strongs="2281" greek="θάλασσα" head="false"/>,
<g beta="PE/LAGOS" strongs="3989" greek="πέλαγος" head="false"/></h2>

<p><g beta="QA/LASSA" strongs="2281" greek="θάλασσα" head="true"/> is the more general
word, indicating <em>the sea</em> or <em>ocean</em> as contrasted with
the land or shore. It may be applied to small bodies of water. <g beta="PE/LAGOS" strongs="3989" greek="πέλαγος" head="true"/> is <em>the open sea</em>,
the uninterrupted expanse of water, in contrast with the portions
broken by islands or with partly inclosed bays. The prominent thought
is said by Trench to be breadth rather than depth. Noteworthy is the
distinction between the two words in <scripRef
href="Matt.18.6">Mat. xviii. 6</scripRef>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="49" heading="To grieve.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="LUPE/W" strongs="3076" greek="λυπέω" />
<definedWord beta="PENQE/W" strongs="3996" greek="πενθέω" />
<definedWord beta="QRHNE/W" strongs="2354" greek="θρηνέω" />
<definedWord beta="KO/PTW" strongs="2875" greek="κόπτω" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 49. To grieve.</h1>

<h2><g beta="LUPE/W" strongs="3076" greek="λυπέω" head="false"/>,
<g beta="PENQE/W" strongs="3996" greek="πενθέω" head="false"/>, <g beta="QRHNE/W" strongs="2354" greek="θρηνέω" head="false"/>, <g beta="KO/PTW" strongs="2875" greek="κόπτω"
head="false"/>.</h2>


<p><g beta="LUPE/W" strongs="3076" greek="λυπέω" head="true"/> is the most general
word, meaning simply <em>to grieve</em>, outwardly or inwardly. <g beta="PENQE/W" strongs="3996" greek="πενθέω" head="true"/> means properly <em>to
lament for the dead</em>. It is also applied to passionate lamentation
of any kind, so great that it cannot be hid. <g beta="QRHNE/W" strongs="2354" greek="θρηνέω" head="true"/> is <em>to give utterance to a dirge</em>
over the dead, either in unstudied words, or in a more elaborate
poem. This word is used by S. in describing David's lament over Saul
and Jonathan. <g beta="KO/PTW" strongs="2875" greek="κόπτω" head="true"/> is
<em>to beat the breast in grief</em>, ordinarily for the dead.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="50" heading="Form, appearance.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="I)DE/A" strongs="2397" greek="ἰδέα" />
<definedWord beta="MORFH/" strongs="3444" greek="μορφή" />
<definedWord beta="SXH=MA" strongs="4976" greek="σχῆμα" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 50. Form, appearance.</h1>

<h2><g beta="I)DE/A" strongs="2397" greek="ἰδέα" head="false"/>, <g beta="MORFH/" strongs="3444" greek="μορφή" head="false"/>, <g beta="SXH=MA" strongs="4976" greek="σχῆμα" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="I)DE/A" strongs="2397" greek="ἰδέα" head="true"/> denotes merely
<em>outward appearance</em>. Both <g beta="MORFH/" strongs="3444" greek="μορφή"
head="true"/> and <g beta="SXH=MA" strongs="4976" greek="σχῆμα" head="true"/> express
something more than that. They too denote outward form, but as
including one’s habits, activities, and modes of action in general. In
<g beta="MORFH/" strongs="3444" greek="μορφή" head="false"/> it is also implied that
the outward form expresses the inner essence, an idea which is absent
from <g beta="SXH=MA" strongs="4976" greek="σχῆμα" head="false"/>. <g beta="MORFH/" strongs="3444" greek="μορφή" head="false"/> expresses the form as that which is
intrinsic and essential, <g beta="SXH=MA" strongs="4976" greek="σχῆμα" head="false"/>
signifies the figure, shape, as that which is more outward and
accidental. Both <g beta="SXH=MA" strongs="4976" greek="σχῆμα" head="false"/> and <g beta="I)DE/A" strongs="2397" greek="ἰδέα" head="false"/> therefore deal with
externals, <g beta="MORFH/" strongs="3444" greek="μορφή" head="false"/> being more
comprehensive than <g beta="I)DE/A" strongs="2397" greek="ἰδέα" head="false"/>,
while <g beta="MORFH/" strongs="3444" greek="μορφή" head="false"/> deals with
externals as expressing that which is internal.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="51" heading="Clothing.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="I(MA/TION" strongs="2440" greek="ἱμάτιον" />
<definedWord beta="XITW/N" strongs="5509" greek="χιτών" />
<definedWord beta="I(MATISMO/S" strongs="2441" greek="ἱματισμός" />
<definedWord beta="XLAMU/S" strongs="5511" greek="χλαμύς" />
<definedWord beta="STOLH/" strongs="4749" greek="στολή" />
<definedWord beta="PODH/RHS" strongs="4158" greek="ποδήρης" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 51. Clothing.</h1>

<h2><g beta="I(MA/TION" strongs="2440" greek="ἱμάτιον" head="false"/>,
<g beta="XITW/N" strongs="5509" greek="χιτών" head="false"/>, <g beta="I(MATISMO/S" strongs="2441" greek="ἱματισμός" head="false"/>, <g beta="XLAMU/S" strongs="5511" greek="χλαμύς"
head="false"/>, <g beta="STOLH/" strongs="4749" greek="στολή" head="false"/>, <g beta="PODH/RHS" strongs="4158" greek="ποδήρης" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="I(MA/TION" strongs="2440" greek="ἱμάτιον" head="true"/> is used in a
general sense to mean <em>clothing</em>, and may thus be applied to
any garment when it is not desired to express its exact nature. In a
more specific use, however, it denotes the large loose outer garment,
<em>a cloak</em>, which ordinarily was worn, but in working was laid
aside. <g beta="XITW/N" strongs="5509" greek="χιτών" head="true"/> is best expressed
by the word <em>tunic</em>. It was a closely fitting under-garment,
usually worn next the skin. At times, especially in working, it was
the only garment worn. A person clothed only in the <g beta="XITW/N" strongs="5509" greek="χιτών" head="false"/> was often called <g beta="GUMNO/S" strongs="1131" greek="γυμνός" head="false"/> (<scripRef
href="John.21.7">Jn. xxi. 7</scripRef>). <g beta="I(MA/TION" strongs="2440" greek="ἱμάτιον" head="false"/> and <g beta="XITW/N" strongs="5509" greek="χιτών"
head="false"/> are often found associated as the upper and under
garment respectively. <g beta="I(MATISMO/S" strongs="2441" greek="ἱματισμός"
head="true"/> does not denote a specific garment, but means
<em>clothing</em>, being used, however, ordinarily only of garments
more or less stately or costly. <g beta="XLAMU/S" strongs="5511" greek="χλαμύς"
head="true"/> is <em>a robe</em> or <em>cloak</em>, it is a technical
expression for a garment of dignity or office. <g beta="STOLH/" strongs="4749" greek="στολή" head="true"/> is any stately robe, ordinarily long,
reaching to the feet or sweeping the ground, often worn by women. <g beta="PODH/RHS" strongs="4158" greek="ποδήρης" head="false"/> was originally an
adjective meaning <em>reaching to the feet</em>. It can hardly be
distinguished in use from <g beta="STOLH/" strongs="4749" greek="στολή"
head="false"/>. It occurs only in <scripRef
href="Rev.1.13">Rev. i. 13</scripRef>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="52" heading="New.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="NE/OS" strongs="3501" greek="νέος" />
<definedWord beta="KAINO/S" strongs="2537" greek="καινός" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 52. New.</h1>

<h2><g beta="NE/OS" strongs="3501" greek="νέος" head="false"/>, <g beta="KAINO/S" strongs="2537" greek="καινός" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="NE/OS" strongs="3501" greek="νέος" head="true"/> is <em>the new</em> as
contemplated under the aspect of time, that which has recently come
into existence. <g beta="KAINO/S" strongs="2537" greek="καινός" head="true"/> is
<em>the new</em> under the aspect of quality, that which has not seen
service. <g beta="KAINO/S" strongs="2537" greek="καινός" head="false"/> therefore
often means new as contrasted with that which has decayed with age, or
is worn out, its opposite then being <g beta="PALAIO/S" strongs="3820" greek="παλαιός"
head="false" ref="true" entry="41"/>.  It sometimes suggests that which is
unusual. It often implies praise, the new as superior to the
old. Occasionally, on the other hand, it implies the opposite, the new
as inferior to that which is old, because the old is familiar or
because it has improved with age. Of course it is evident that both <g beta="NE/OS" strongs="3501" greek="νέος" head="false"/> and <g beta="KAINO/S" strongs="2537" greek="καινός" head="false"/> may sometimes be applied to the same
object, but from different points of view.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="53" heading="Labor.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="MO/XQOS" strongs="3449" greek="μόχθος" />
<definedWord beta="PO/NOS" strongs="4192" greek="πόνος" />
<definedWord beta="KO/POS" strongs="2873" greek="κόπος" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 53. Labor.</h1>

<h2><g beta="MO/XQOS" strongs="3449" greek="μόχθος" head="false"/>, <g beta="PO/NOS" strongs="4192" greek="πόνος" head="false"/>, <g beta="KO/POS" strongs="2873" greek="κόπος" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="MO/XQOS" strongs="3449" greek="μόχθος" head="true"/> is <em>labor</em>,
hard and often painful. It is the ordinary word for common labor which
is the usual lot of humanity.  <g beta="PO/NOS" strongs="4192" greek="πόνος"
head="true"/> is <em>labor</em> which demands one’s whole strength. It
is therefore applied to labors of an unusual kind, specially wearing
or painful. In classical Greek it was the usual word employed to
describe the labors of Hercules. <g beta="KO/POS" strongs="2873" greek="κόπος"
head="true"/> denotes <em>the weariness</em> which results from labor,
or labor considered from the standpoint of the resulting
weariness.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="54" heading="Drunkenness, drinking.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="ME/QH" strongs="3178" greek="μέθη" />
<definedWord beta="PO/TOS" strongs="4224" greek="πότος" />
<definedWord beta="OI)NOFLUGI/A" strongs="3632" greek="οἰνοφλυγία" />
<definedWord beta="KW=MOS" strongs="2970" greek="κῶμος" />
<definedWord beta="KRAIPA/LH" strongs="2897" greek="κραιπάλη" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 54. Drunkenness, drinking.</h1>

<h2><g beta="ME/QH" strongs="3178" greek="μέθη" head="false"/>, <g beta="PO/TOS" strongs="4224" greek="πότος" head="false"/>, <g beta="OI)NOFLUGI/A" strongs="3632" greek="οἰνοφλυγία" head="false"/>, <g beta="KW=MOS" strongs="2970" greek="κῶμος"
head="false"/>, <g beta="KRAIPA/LH" strongs="2897" greek="κραιπάλη" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="ME/QH" strongs="3178" greek="μέθη" head="true"/> is the ordinary word
for <em>drunkenness</em>. <g beta="PO/TOS" strongs="4224" greek="πότος" head="true"/>
is rather concrete, <em>a drinking, carousing</em>. <g beta="OI)NOFLUGI/A" strongs="3632" greek="οἰνοφλυγία" head="true"/> is a prolonged
condition of drunkenness, <em>a debauch</em>. <g beta="KW=MOS" strongs="2970" greek="κῶμος" head="true"/> includes <em>riot</em> and
<em>revelry</em>a, usually as arising from drunkenness. <g beta="KRAIPA/LH" strongs="2897" greek="κραιπάλη" head="true"/> denotes <em>the
sickness</em> and <em>discomfort</em> resulting from drunkenness.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="55" heading="War, battle.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="PO/LEMOS" strongs="4171" greek="πόλεμος" />
<definedWord beta="MA/XH" strongs="3163" greek="μάχη" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 55. War, battle.</h1>

<h2><g beta="PO/LEMOS" strongs="4171" greek="πόλεμος" head="false"/>, <g beta="MA/XH" strongs="3163" greek="μάχη" head="false"/>.</h2>



<p><g beta="PO/LEMOS" strongs="4171" greek="πόλεμος" head="true"/>
ordinarily means <em>war</em>, <em>i.e.</em>, the whole course of
hostilities; <g beta="MA/XH" strongs="3163" greek="μάχη"
head="true"/>, <em>battle</em>, a single engagement. It is also true
that <g beta="MA/XH" strongs="3163" greek="μάχη" head="false"/> has
often the weaker force of <em>strife</em> or <em>contention</em> which
is very seldom found in <g beta="PO/LEMOS" strongs="4171"
greek="πόλεμος" head="false"/>.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="56" heading="Basket.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="SPURI/S" strongs="4711" greek="σπυρίς" />
<definedWord beta="KO/FINOS" strongs="2894" greek="κόφινος" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 56. Basket.</h1>

<h2><g beta="SPURI/S" strongs="4711" greek="σπυρίς" head="false"/>, <g beta="KO/FINOS" strongs="2894" greek="κόφινος" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p>These words in the N.T. are used with an evident purpose to
discriminate between them. The distinction, however, does not seem to
have been chiefly one of size, as some have thought, but of use. <g beta="SPURI/S" strongs="4711" greek="σπυρίς" head="true"/> is usually a basket for
food, <em>a lunchbasket</em>, <em>a hamper</em>, while <g beta="KO/FINOS" strongs="2894" greek="κόφινος" head="true"/> is a more general term for
basket. The descriptions of the two miracles of feeding the multitude
use always different words in the two cases, see <em>e.g.</em>
<scripRef href="Mark.8.19-Mark.8.20">Mar. viii. 19, 20</scripRef>.</p>



</content>
</entry>

<entry number="57" heading="It is necessary.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="DEI=" strongs="1163" greek="δεῖ" />
<definedWord beta="O)FEI/LW" strongs="3784" greek="ὀφείλω" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 57. It is necessary.</h1>

<h2><g beta="DEI=" strongs="1163" greek="δεῖ" head="false"/>, <g beta="O)FEI/LW" strongs="3784" greek="ὀφείλω" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="DEI=" strongs="1163" greek="δεῖ" head="true"/>, the third person of <g beta="DE/W" strongs="1210" greek="δέω" head="false"/>, is commonly used
impersonally in classical Greek. This usage is less common, but
frequent, in the N.T. <g beta="DEI=" strongs="1163" greek="δεῖ" head="false"/>
indicates a necessity in the nature of things rather than a personal
obligation, it describes that which <em>must</em> be done.  <g beta="O)FEI/LW" strongs="3784" greek="ὀφείλω" head="true"/> indicates rather the
personal obligation, it is that which is proper, something that
<em>ought</em> to be done.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="58" heading="Tax.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="FO/ROS" strongs="5411" greek="φόρος" />
<definedWord beta="TE/LOS" strongs="5056" greek="τέλος" />
<definedWord beta="KH=NSOS" strongs="2778" greek="κῆνσος" />
<definedWord beta="DI/DRAXMON" strongs="1323" greek="δίδραχμον" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 58. Tax.</h1>

<h2><g beta="FO/ROS" strongs="5411" greek="φόρος" head="false"/>, <g beta="TE/LOS" strongs="5056" greek="τέλος" head="false"/>, <g beta="KH=NSOS" strongs="2778" greek="κῆνσος" head="false"/>, <g beta="DI/DRAXMON" strongs="1323" greek="δίδραχμον"
head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="FO/ROS" strongs="5411" greek="φόρος" head="true"/> indicates <em>a direct
tax</em> which was levied annually on houses, lands, and persons, and
paid usually in produce. <g beta="TE/LOS" strongs="5056" greek="τέλος" head="false"/>
is <em>an indirect tax</em> on merchandise, which was collected at
piers, harbors, and gates of cities. It was similar to modern import
duties. <g beta="KH=NSOS" strongs="2778" greek="κῆνσος" head="true"/>, originally an
enrollment of property and persons, came to mean a <em>poll-tax</em>,
levied annually on individuals by the Roman government. <g beta="DI/DRAXMON" strongs="1323" greek="δίδραχμον" head="true"/> was the coin used to
pay an annual tax levied by the religious leaders of Israel for the
purpose of defraying the general expenses of the Temple.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="59" heading="Tax-collector.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="TELW/NHS" strongs="5057" greek="τελώνης" />
<definedWord beta="A)RXITELW/NHS" strongs="754" greek="ἀρχιτελώνης" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 59. Tax-collector.</h1>

<h2><g beta="TELW/NHS" strongs="5057" greek="τελώνης" head="false"/>, <g beta="A)RXITELW/NHS" strongs="754" greek="ἀρχιτελώνης" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p>The Roman system of collecting taxes, especially the <g beta="TE/LOS" strongs="5056" greek="τέλος" head="false" ref="true" entry="58"/>, in
their provinces, included ordinarily three grades of officials.  There
was the highest, called in Latin <em>publicanus</em>, who paid a sum
of money for the taxes of a certain province, and then exacted that
and as much more as he could from the province.  This man lived in
Rome. Then there were the <em>submagistri</em>, who had charge each of
a certain portion of territory, and who lived in the provinces. Then
there were the <em>portitores</em>, the actual custom-house officers,
who did the real work of collecting the taxes. The N.T. word <g beta="TELW/NHS" strongs="5057" greek="τελώνης" head="true"/> is used to describe one of
the <em>portitores</em>, it is the lowest of these three grades. It
does not correspond to the Latin <em>publicanus</em>, and the word
<em>publican</em> used to translate it in A.V. and R.V. is apt to be
misleading, <em>tax-collector</em> would be better. <g beta="A)RXITELW/NHS" strongs="754" greek="ἀρχιτελώνης" head="true"/>, only occurring in
<scripRef href="Luk.19.2">Lu.  xix. 2</scripRef>, evidently describes
a higher otficial than <g beta="TELW/NHS" strongs="5057" greek="τελώνης"
head="false"/>, and is probably one of the <em>submagistri</em>, the
next higher grade.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="60" heading="Child.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="TE/KNON" strongs="5043" greek="τέκνον" />
<definedWord beta="UI(O/S" strongs="5207" greek="υἱός" />
<definedWord beta="PAI=S" strongs="3816" greek="παῖς" />
<definedWord beta="PAIDI/ON" strongs="3813" greek="παιδίον" />
<definedWord beta="PAIDA/RION" strongs="3808" greek="παιδάριον" />
<definedWord beta="PAIDI/SKH" strongs="3814" greek="παιδίσκη" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 60. Child.</h1>

<h2><g beta="TE/KNON" strongs="5043" greek="τέκνον" head="false"/>, <g beta="UI(O/S" strongs="5207" greek="υἱός" head="false"/>, <g beta="PAI=S" strongs="3816" greek="παῖς" head="false"/>, <g beta="PAIDI/ON" strongs="3813" greek="παιδίον" head="false"/>, <g beta="PAIDA/RION" strongs="3808" greek="παιδάριον" head="false"/>, <g beta="PAIDI/SKH" strongs="3814" greek="παιδίσκη" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p><g beta="TE/KNON" strongs="5043" greek="τέκνον" head="true"/> and <g beta="UI(O/S" strongs="5207" greek="υἱός" head="true"/> both point to parentage. <g beta="TE/KNON" strongs="5043" greek="τέκνον" head="false"/>, however, emphasizes the idea of descent,
giving prominence to the physical and outward aspects; while <g beta="UI(O/S" strongs="5207" greek="υἱός" head="false"/> emphasizes the idea of
relationship, and considers especially the inward, ethical, and legal
aspects. <g beta="PAI=S" strongs="3816" greek="παῖς" head="true"/> as well as <g beta="TE/KNON" strongs="5043" greek="τέκνον" head="false"/> emphasizes the idea of
descent, but gives especial prominence to age, denoting a child as one
who is young. <g beta="PAI=S" strongs="3816" greek="παῖς" head="true"/> is also
often used of a servant. The number of years covered by the term <g beta="PAI=S" strongs="3816" greek="παῖς" head="false"/> is quite indefinite.  Its
diminutives <g beta="PAIDI/ON" strongs="3813" greek="παιδίον" head="true"/> and <g beta="PAIDA/RION" strongs="3808" greek="παιδάριον" head="false"/> are used without
appreciable difference to denote a young child. (<g beta="PAIDI/SKOS" greek="παιδίσκος" head="false" ref="external"/> in classical Greek and) <g beta="PAIDI/SKH" strongs="3814" greek="παιδίσκη" head="true"/>, in which the diminutive
force is largely lost, cover the years of late childhood and early
youth.</p>


</content>
</entry>

<entry number="61" heading="Tribe, family, household.">
<definedWords>
<definedWord beta="FULH/" strongs="5443" greek="φυλή" />
<definedWord beta="PATRIA/" strongs="3965" greek="πατριά" />
<definedWord beta="OI)=KOS" strongs="3624" greek="οἶκος" /></definedWords>
<content>
<h1>§ 61. Tribe, family, household.</h1>

<h2><g beta="FULH/" strongs="5443" greek="φυλή" head="false"/>, <g beta="PATRIA/" strongs="3965" greek="πατριά" head="false"/>, <g beta="OI)=KOS" strongs="3624" greek="οἶκος" head="false"/>.</h2>

<p>These words form a series. <g beta="FULH/" strongs="5443" greek="φυλή"
head="true"/> is sometimes <em>a race</em>, <em>nation</em>, but
usually <em>a tribe</em>, such as one of the twelve tribes of Israel,
descended from the twelve sons of Jacob. <g beta="PATRIA/" strongs="3965" greek="πατριά" head="true"/> is a smaller division within the tribe, it
is an association of families closely related, in the N.T. generally
used of those descended from a particular one of the sons of Jacob's
sons. <g beta="OI)=KOS" strongs="3624" greek="οἶκος" head="true"/> is yet narrower,
<em>household</em>, including all the inmates of a single house, being
the unit of organization.</p>
</content>
</entry>

</lexicon>
